Guide to the Israel Shreve Revolutionary War Letters
University of Houston Libraries
Israel Shreve Revolutionary War Letters
1768-1894
10/1965-001
Shreve, Israel, 1739-1799
0.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Other Information: Uploaded to TARO, 2005. For more information please see https://txarchives.org/uhsc/finding_aids/00024.xml.
This 76-item collection mainly consists of letters written to and from Colonel Israel Shreve between the years of 1776 and 1793, with the bulk of the correspondence taking place between the years 1777 and 1780. Most of the correspondence is between Shreve and other officers in George Washington's Continental Army, and was written while Shreve was Colonel of the Second Regiment of New Jersey during the Revolutionary War. The collection is divided into two series, one of the Colonel Israel Shreve Correspondence, and one of Miscellaneous materials, including other correspondence.
Biographical Information:
Colonel Israel Shreve was born in 1739 in New Jersey. Before rising to a position of military leadership in General George Washington's Continental Army during the American Revolution, he worked as a farmer in Gloucester County.
On October 31, 1775, Shreve was appointed Lieutenant Colonel of the Second Regiment of New Jersey troops. On November 28, 1776, he was promoted to Colonel for the reorganized line, which was now known as the Second New Jersey Regiment, Second Establishment.
The 2nd N.J. Regiment fought at the Battle of Brandywine on September 11, 1777, and at the Battle of Germantown on October 4, 1777. They also spent the cold winter of 1777, short of clothing and food supplies, with Washington's troops at Valley Forge.
On June 28, 1778, Shreve played a part in the strange events of the Battle of Monmouth. Major General Charles Lee led the advance column against the British troops, but gave his men hasty orders to retreat after being startled by a counterattack from the British. He did not give word of his decision to General Washington, who was following behind him with the main army. As an angry Washington met up with columns of confused troops falling back from the front, he pressed the approaching Colonel Israel Shreve for an explanation. "Colonel Shreve answered in a very significant manner, smiling, that he did not know, but that he had retreated by order, he did not say by whose order." Following the Battle of Monmouth, Lee was court-martialled and removed from command.
In July of 1779, Shreve and the 2nd N.J. Regiment joined Major General John Sullivan in his campaign against the Tory-allied Iroquois Indians. Shreve was appointed commander of the expedition's base at Fort Sullivan at Tioga, while General Sullivan and his troops went on a punishing spree against the Indians, burning 40 of their towns and destroying corn, vegetables, and orchards.
According to one source, Shreve was "immensely fat" and such an incompetent officer that in December of 1780 Washington declined to promote him to Brigadier General, saying, "Here I drop the curtain." Shreve retired from the army on January 1, 1781, but for inexplicable reasons remained in command through the rest of the month. In early January, troops in the Pennsylvania Line mutinied over lack of pay and other grievances. When the New Jersey Line followed suit on January 20, Shreve by all accounts botched or neglected handling the situation. At the end of January, Elias Dayton took over as Colonel.
Shreve apparently participated in the General Assembly of New Jersey following the end of his military career. In April 1783, members of the New Jersey Line requested that he represent them to the Assembly on the issue of receiving five years' full pay at the end of their service, rather than half-pay for life.
Shreve returned to farming after the war, eventually settling in the west with his wife and children. He died in 1799.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
United States. Continental Army. New York Artillery Regiment, 2nd
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence
Geographic Name:
United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783
Personal Name:
Shreve, Israel, 1739-1799; Washington, George, 1732-1799
Acquisition Information:
The greater part of the collection was donated to the University of Houston Libraries in 1965 by Emily Scott Evans. Items 9, 10, and 37 (the George Washington letters and document) were added to the collection by her daughter Mrs. Alice Evans Pratt between 1968 and 1976.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
Israel Shreve Revolutionary War Letters, 1768-1894 digital collection
http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/p15195coll12
Scope and Contents
This 76-item collection mainly consists of letters written to and from Colonel Israel Shreve between the years of 1776 and 1793, with the bulk of the correspondence taking place between the years 1777 and 1780. Most of the correspondence is between Shreve and other officers in George Washington's Continental Army, and was written while Shreve was Colonel of the Second Regiment of New Jersey during the Revolutionary War. The collection is divided into two series, one of the Colonel Israel Shreve Correspondence, and one of Miscellaneous materials, including other correspondence.
Typed transcriptions of these items are available in the bound book The Shreve Papers 1776-1792, which is located in the collection file.
A set of photocopies of the Israel Shreve holdings of Rutgers University is also available for use. The Rutgers collection includes letters to and from Shreve, as well as documents pertaining to him, which are contemporary with those of this collection. There are 340 photocopied items total.
Detailed List of Contents
- Colonel Israel Shreve Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains mostly correspondence, plus a few maps and documents. Among the correspondents are General George Washington, Alexander Hamilton, General A.W. Anthony Wayne, and General Henry Lee. Some correspondence is between Shreve and his wife Mary and his brothers Caleb and William. The items in this series are arranged chronologically.
  - General Philip Schuyler to Shreve, Albany, April 5, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lieutenant Colonel Tench Tilghman, aide to General Washington, to Colonel Alexander Scammell, Thursday [approximately 1776-1781] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Major General Israel Putnam to Shreve, Princeton, April 5, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brigadier General William Maxwell to Shreve, Westfield, April 11, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Account of illness in camps and hospital by Shreve, Chimney Point, opposite Crown Point, New York, Poem or song, August 4 [1777], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Adjutant General Timothy Pickering to Major General Lord Sterling, or, in his absence, to Brigadier General William Maxwell, in camp, August 10, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Staff of the Army as of November 1, 1777, November 2, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Governor William Livingston to Shreve, Trenton, March 23, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General George Washington to Shreve, Headquarters Valley Forge, April 6, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General George Washington to Shreve, authorization for the court-martial of William Seeds, Headquarters Valley Forge, April 6, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General David Forman, Chief of Washington's Secret Service in New Jersey, Barnegat, to Shreve, April 7, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Colonel Israel Shreve to General George Washington (draft), Mount Holly, April 9, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Colonel David Rhea to Shreve, Freehold, April 17, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Major General Philemon Dickinson to Shreve, Trenton, May 25, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Major General Philemon Dickinson to Shreve, Trenton, May 27, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Major Richard Howell, with note added by Captain John Peck, October 5, 1778, October 18, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hand-drawn map of Fort Sullivan at Tioga, approximately May-November 1779 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Alexander Hamilton to Shreve, Headquarters Middlebrook, May 26, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - James McHenry to Shreve or the officer commanding at Elizabethtown, Headquarters Middlebrook, May 27, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Colonel Israel Shreve to General George Washington (draft), Elizabethtown, May 27, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Colonel M. Furman to Shreve, Pitts-town, June 10, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Major Richard Howell to Shreve, June 12, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Colonel Israel Shreve to Mary Shreve, Wyoming [Valley], July 8, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Peter Scull to Shreve, War Office, July 12, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - General Edward Hand to Major General John Sullivan, Nesquepee Falls, July 22, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Caleb Shreve to Colonel Israel Shreve, Mansfield, July 24, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Colonel Israel Shreve to Mary Shreve, Fort Sullivan at Tioga, August 28, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Benjamin Bruen, Secretary to Major General John Sullivan, to Shreve, Headquarters Newtown, August 30, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Colonel William D'Hart to Shreve, Newtown, account of the defeat of the Indians at Newtown, August 30, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Colonel Zebulon Butler to Shreve, Wyoming [Valley], September 3, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - [Major John Ross], Headquarters Kanadasegea [Canadaigua], September 8, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Colonel Zebulon Butler to Shreve, Wyoming [Valley], September 10, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Robert L. Hooper, Jr. to Shreve, Easton, September 15, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Major General John Sullivan to Shreve, Headquarters Connawolowhalley, September 25, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Major John Ross to Shreve, Fort Reid, September 25, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Captain William Shute to Shreve, Camp Fort Reed, September 26, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - General George Washington to Shreve, Headquarters Morristown, January 16, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - General Henry ("Light Horse Harry") Lee to Shreve, Burlington, May 12, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Colonel William D'Hart to Shreve, May 20, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Colonel Israel Shreve to Mary Shreve, Jersey Camp, Bergon County, July 27, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Colonel John Stark to Shreve, November 24, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - (Assistant Adjutant General) John Stagg, Extract from General Orders, Headquarters New Windsor, December 11, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Colonel (Adjutant General) Alexander Scammell, Transcript of General Orders, Headquarters New Windsor, December 19, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - General Anthony Wayne to Shreve, Mount Kemble, with note to Shreve, December 22, 1780, December 25, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - P. Peres to Shreve, Ramabough, December 26, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Colonel (Adjutant General) Alexander Scammell, Extract from General Orders, Headquarters New Windsor, December 31, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Jacob Arnold to Jersey officers, Morristown, [January 1,] 1781 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - General Anthony Wayne to the officer commis, the Jersey Brigade, Mount Kemble, January 2, 1780 [1781] (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Ebenezer Elmer, Brigadier General New Jersey Militia, to Shreve, Camp near New Windsor, November 4, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - John Combs, N.J. Captain in Revolution, to Shreve, Sunday morning, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - John Beatty, member of the Continental Congress, Major, Sixth Penn. Regiment in Revolution, to Shreve, Annapolis, April 3, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - [OVS] Petition to Congress for lands on the Ohio River, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - John Cox to Shreve, Bloomsbury, September 18, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Colonel William Shreve to Colonel Israel Shreve, Westmoreland County, November 20, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Colonel William Shreve to Colonel Israel Shreve, Alexandria, September 14, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Colonel Israel Shreve to Mary Shreve, Pittsburgh, December 30, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Colonel Israel Shreve to Mary Shreve, Fort Harmar, Muskingum, January 6, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Colonel Israel Shreve to Mary Shreve, New Madrid, April 6, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Hand-drawn map of "Lancelegrace," possibly in the hand of Colonel Israel Shreve, [1789] (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Caleb Shreve to Colonel Israel Shreve, Mansfield, April 27, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - [Printed broadside], Extract from the Minutes of the Proceedings of a General Meeting of the Citizens of Philadelphia, held in the State House Yard, Monday the 30th of July, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Printed circular letter to Colonel Israel Shreve, signed by Thomas McKean, James Hutchinson, John Barclay, A.J. Dallas, Jared Ingersoll, and Hilary Baker, Philadelphia, McKean was a signer of the Declaration of Independence and Governor of Pennsylvania, August 3, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Colonel Israel Shreve to Nathan Brown, January 12, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Caleb Shreve, Jr. to Colonel Israel Shreve, Mount Pleasant, June 20, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - [OVS] Hand-drawn map of City of Symmes, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Miscellaneous
  This series contains miscellaneous items dating from 1768 to 1894. These include letters and documents pertaining to Shreve's relatives, two copies of letters from George Washington which were anonymously handwritten at a much later date, and several unrelated items from the same time period. The items in this series are arranged chronologically.
  - Reed, Pardon of Theodosia Hickman by Britain for crime of forni-, Burlington, [--] 30, 1768 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Thomas Broderick, promissory note to John Atkinson, with note by Atkinson signing over to Colonel William Shreve, October 11, 1774, October 26, 1774 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - [Washington, George], copy of letter, Headquarters Valley Forge, May 23, 1778 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Mary Shreve to Lucky Hancock, Newark, February 24, 1779 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - [Washington, George], copy of letter, Headquarters Middlebrook, May 24, 1779 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Mark Seer, legal document, November 23, 1807 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Henry M. Shreve to Mary Shreve, St. Louis, added note from Henry M. Shreve to his sister, August 19, 1810 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Masonic membership certificate for Able Dunham, Triluminar Lodge No. 117, in the vicinity of Bruce's Mill, Virginia, March 19, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Philip A. Bruce, Richmond, Virginia, June 19, 1894, with note added in reply by Henry L. Scott, July 2, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - [Abraham Dyson], mathematical problem, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Portion of document with name of Colonel Israel Shreve, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)